A Guide to the National Visitor Center (Washington, D.C.) Collection, 1966-1977, n.d. (likely 1970s)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
National Visitor Center (Washington, D.C.) Collection, 1966-1977, n.d. (likely 1970s)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Drumheller, Warren D.
Ms2017-002
5.1 Cubic Feet 3 boxes; 7 oversize folders; 1 framed photograph
The National Visitor Center (Washington, D.C.) Collection includes materials concerning the projected construction of the National Visitor Center at Union Station in Washington D.C. in the 1970s. The collection includes correspondence, records, images, memorabilia, maps, and architecture drawings of the center, which was only open briefly from 1976 to 1978.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The National Visitor Center (Washington, DC) Collection was donated to Special Collections in July 2015.
Scope and Content
The National Visitor Center (Washington, D.C.) Collection includes materials concerning the projected construction of the National Visitor Center at Union Station in Washington D.C. in the 1970s. The collection includes correspondence, records, images, memorabilia, maps, and architecture drawings of the center, which was open briefly from 1976 to 1978. This collection is organized into four series.
Series I: Documents includes materials from about 1972 to 1975, as well as some undated materials, likely from the same time period. This series contains paperwork relating to the development of the project: contracts, meeting notes, planning documents, materials from lawsuits, and Federal reference manuals. The first half of this series is arranged in chronological order. The second half, which includes the undated materials, is arranged by subject and folders are in alphabetical order by title.
Series II: Images contains photographs, negatives, and slides from construction, events held in the space, and a large framed photograph of a model. Although undated, they are most likely from the 1970s. This series is arranged by format and then by subject, if known.
Series III: Newspapers consists of whole papers and clippings from 1969-1977 that reference development, planning, construction, and the completed project. They come from a variety of newspapers. This series is arranged chronologically.
Series IV: Drawings, Plans, & Plats includes a range of architectural materials from 1972 to 1976. There are full and half-size drawings, architectural plans, and location plat maps. There are two full-size sets of prints, as well as a site plan and several specific sections/views. This series is arranged in chronological order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
William Drumheller, who worked on this project, graduated from Virginia Polytechnic Institute in 1949. Special Collections houses two collections relating to Drumheller:
Warren D. Drumheller Papers, Ms1963-004. Finding aid available online.
William F. Drumheller, Jr. Collection, Ms2013-007. Finding aid available online.
VPI Poster created by Drumheller, 1942, Art-351. Record for item available online.
In addition, Special Collections also includes three engineering drawings completed by Drumheller between 1947-1949. These items are unprocessed, but will eventually be added to Ms2013-007. For now, they are available upon request.
Index Terms
Subjects:
National Visitor Center; Architecture
Contents List
- Series I: Documents, 1972-1975, n.d (likely 1970s)
  - Dated materials, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dated materials (1/2), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dated materials (2/2), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dated materials (1/5), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dated materials (2/5), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dated materials (3/5), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dated materials (4/5), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dated materials (5/5), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dated materials, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Contracts and Agreements (1/2) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Contracts and Agreements (2/2) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Department of the Interior (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Drumheller - Owner Representative (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Law Suits (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - National Visitor Center Building Information (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - No Date, Misc. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notes and Memorabilia for the National Visitor Center (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Program Elements (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Proposal to Operate and Maintain a Parking Facility at the National Visitor Center (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Reference Manual - Calculating the Return on Proposed Projects, Equipment, or Plant Facilities (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Reference Manual - Landscaping for Gallery Place and Judiciary Square Stations (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Reference Manual - Regulation of Rates of Common Carriers (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series II: Images
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "National Visitor Center" (framed photograph of model) (Item 1)
  - Negatives - Christmas Party (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Negatives - Christmas Party & National Visitor Center Construction (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Negatives - National Visitor Center Construction (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Slides - National Visitor Center (1/2) (Box 2, Box 2a)
  - Slides - National Visitor Center (2/2) (Box 2, Box 2b)
- Series III: Newspapers, 1969-1977
  - Newspapers, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Newspapers, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Newspapers, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Newspapers, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Newspapers, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Newspapers, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Newspapers, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Washington Star, 8 March 1975 (Folder 1)
- Series IV: Drawings, Plans, & Plats, 1972-1976
  - Washington Terminal Company Tracks and Facilities, 15 March 1966 (Folder 2)
  - Main Terminal Level, 1971 (Folder 3)
  - North-South Section thru Ramp 'E-E', 1973 (Folder 3)
  - Site Plan, 1972 (Folder 3)
  - Half-size National Visitor Prints, 1973 (Folder 4)
  - Noraloco Corp. Proposals 1-3, 1974 (Folder 5)
  - Building Location Plat, 1974 (Folder 5)
  - East-West Section thru Ramp Looking North, 1975 (Folder 6)
  - Post Office Bridge, 1975 (Folder 6)
  - Main Parking Level, 1975 (Folder 6)
  - Ground Level, 1975 (Folder 6)
  - Full-size National Visitor Center Prints, 1976 (Folder 7)
  - Full-size National Visitor Center Prints, 1970s (Box 3)